<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe chronicle, of all the kinges of Scotland declaring in what yeare of the worlde, and of Christ, they began to reigne, how long they reigned, of what qualities they were, and how they died.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11720</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22007</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116893</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852108</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852108</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17415</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11720)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17415)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1155:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe chronicle, of all the kinges of Scotland declaring in what yeare of the worlde, and of Christ, they began to reigne, how long they reigned, of what qualities they were, and how they died.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>45, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edward Raban, for David Melvill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Aberdene :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A.j." and ornaments; the last leaf contains rows of ornaments.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The kings of Scotland.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  Kings and rulers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  To 1603 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  James VI, 1567-1625 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:17415:1"/>
            <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
               <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17415:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17415:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal coat of arms of the kingdom of Scotland, a lion rampant within a double tressure flory counter-flory</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:17415:2"/>
            <head>A Briefe Chronicle, of all the Kings of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, ſince it was firſt <hi>inhabited, vntill this preſent Yeare</hi> 1623.</head>
            <p n="1">I. <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>ERGVS, The Firſt KING of SCOTLAND, the Sonne of FERQVHARD, a Prince of IRELAND, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to reigne in the yeare of the Worlde 3641: before the comming of our Saviour Ieſus Chriſt 330 yeares: in the firſt yeare of the 112 Olympiade: and in the 421 yeare of the building of <hi>Rome:</hi> about the beginning of the thirde Monarchie of the <hi>Grecians,</hi> when <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw <hi>Darius Codomannus,</hi> the laſt Monarch of <hi>Perſia.</hi> Hee was a valiant Prince, and died Ship-broken vpon the Sea-coaſte of <hi>Ireland,</hi> in the 25 yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:17415:3"/>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Feritharis,</hi> Brother to <hi>Fergus,</hi> began to reigne in the yeare of the world 3666: in the yeare before the comming of Chriſt 305. Hee was a good Iuſtitiar: in whoſe time there was a Lawe made, That if the ſonnes of the King departed were ſo young that they could not rule; then, in that caſe, the neareſt in blood ſhould reigne, beeing in age ſufficient for Governement: and then after his death, the Kings Children ſhould ſucceede. Which Lawe continued vntill <hi>Kenneth</hi> the thirds dayes, almoſt 1025 years. Hee was ſlaine by the meanes of <hi>Ferlegus, Fergus</hi> his brothers ſonne, in the fifteenth yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>Mainus,</hi> King <hi>Fergus</hi> ſonne, ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to his fathers brother, in the yeare of the worlde 3680: and in the yeare before the comming of Chriſt 291. Hee was a wyſe and good King: and died peaceablie in the twentie &amp; ninth yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="4">IIII. <hi>Dornadilla</hi> ſucceeded to his father <hi>Mainus,</hi> in the yeare of the worlde 3709: in the yeare before the comming of Chriſt 262. Hee was a good King, who made the firſt Lawes concerning Hunting: and died peaceablie, in the twentie and eight yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:17415:3"/>
            <p n="5">V. <hi>Nothatus</hi> ſucceeded to his brother <hi>Dornadilla,</hi> in the yeare of the worlde 3738: and in the yeare before the comming of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt 233. Hee was a greedie and a cruell Tyrant: and was ſlaine by <hi>Dovalus,</hi> one of his Nobles, in the twentieth yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. <hi>Reutherus,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Dornadilla,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to reigne in the yeare of the worlde 3758: in the yeare before the comming of Chriſt 213. Hee was a good King, and died peaceablie, in the twentie and ſixt yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. <hi>Reutha</hi> ſucceeded to his brother <hi>Reutherus,</hi> in the yeare of the world 3784: in the yeare before the comming of Chriſt 187. Hee was a good King: who after he had ruled fourteene years, left the governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Kingdome, even of his owne accord, and lived a private lyfe.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. <hi>Thereus,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Reutherus,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to reigne in the yeare of the worlde 3798: in the yeare before the comming of Chriſt 173. He was an vnwyſe and cruell Tyrant: who was expelled, and baniſhed the Realme, by his owne Nobles, in the twelft yeare of his reigne: and <hi>Conanus,</hi> a wyſe and graue Senator, was made Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17415:4"/>of the Lande. And <hi>Thereus</hi> died in exyle, in the Citie of <hi>Yorke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">IX. <hi>Ioſina</hi> ſucceeded his brother <hi>Thereus,</hi> in the yeare of the world 3810. In the yeare before Chriſt 161. Hee was a quiet and good Prince. A good medicinar and Herbiſter. He died in peace in the twentie foure yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="10">X. <hi>Finnanus, Ioſina</hi> his ſonne, beganne to reigne in the yeare of the world 3834. In the yeare before Chriſt 137. A good King. He was much giuen to the ſuperſtitious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of the <hi>Druydes.</hi> He died in peace in the 30 yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. <hi>Durstus, Finnanus</hi> ſonne, ſucceeded to his Father in the yeare of the world 3864. In the yeare before Chriſt 107. A cruell and a Traiterous Tyrant, ſlaine by his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles in Battell, in the 9 Yeare of his reigne</p>
            <p n="12">XII. <hi>Evenus</hi> 1. ſucceded to his brother <hi>Durſtus,</hi> in the yeare of the world three thouſand, eight hundred, ſeventie three. In the yeare before the cumming of Chriſt, 98 yeares. A wiſe, juſt, and vertuous prince: He died peaceably in the 19 yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. <hi>Gillus, Evenus</hi> baſtard ſonne, ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17415:4"/>to his father, in the yeare of the world 3892. In the yeare before Chriſt 79. A craftie tyrant, ſlame in battell by <hi>Cadallus,</hi> in the 2 yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="14">XIIII. <hi>Euenus</hi> 2. <hi>Dovallus</hi> ſonne, King <hi>Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanus</hi> brother, began to reigne in the yeare of the world 3894. In the yeare before the comming of Chriſt 77. A good and ciuill King. Hee died in peace in the ſeuenteene yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="15">XV. <hi>Ederus, Dochamus</hi> ſonne, <hi>Durſtus</hi> ſonne, began to reigne in the yeare of the Worlde 3911. In the yeare before the comming of Chriſt 60. A wiſe, Valiant and good Prince. He died in the 48. yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="16">XVI. <hi>Evenus</hi> 3. ſucceeded to his Father <hi>Ederus</hi> in the yeare of the world, three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, nine hundred 59. In the yeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the comming of Chriſt 12. A luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and Covetous wicked King. Hee was taken by his Nobles, and Impriſoned, and died in priſon, in the ſeaventh yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="17">XVII. <hi>Metellanus, Ederus</hi> brothers ſonne, began to reigne in the yeare of the world 3966. Foure yeares before Chriſts Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. A verie modeſt and good King. He
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17415:5"/>died in the 39 yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="18">XVIII. <hi>Caractacus, Cadallarius</hi> and <hi>Eropeia Metellanus</hi> ſiſters ſonne, began to reigne in the yeare of the world 4005. In the yeare of Chriſt 35. Hee was a wiſe and valiant King, and reigned 20 yeares.</p>
            <p n="19">XIX. <hi>Corbredus</hi> 1. ſucceeded to his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Caractacus,</hi> In the yeare of the worlde 4025. In the yeare of Chriſt 55. A wiſe King, and a good Inſtitiar. He died in peace in the 18. yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="20">XX. <hi>Dardannus,</hi> Nephew to <hi>Metellanus,</hi> began to reigne, In the veare of the world 4042. In the yeare of Chriſt 72. A cruell tyrant. He was taken in battell, and behea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by his owne Subjectes, in the fourth yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="21">XXI. <hi>Corbredus</hi> 2. ſur-named <hi>Galius, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brodus</hi> ſonne, began to reigne in they care of the world 4046. In the yeare of Chriſt 76. A valiant and worthy King: for hee had many warres with the <hi>Romaines,</hi> and was oft victorious over them. He died in peace in the 35. yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="22">XXII. <hi>Lugthacus,</hi> ſucceeded to his father <hi>Corbredus</hi> 2. In the yeare of the world 4080. In the yeare of Chriſt 110. A lecherous bloodie tyrant. Hee was ſlaine by his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17415:5"/>in the 3. yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="23">XXIII. <hi>Mogallus, Corbredus</hi> 2. ſiſters ſon. Hee beganne to reigne in the yeare of the world 4083. In the yeare of Chriſt 113. A good King, and victorious, in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his reigne, But in the ende of his life, became inclyned to tyranny, leachery and covetouſneſſe, and was ſlayne by his Nobles in the 36 yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="24">XXIIII. <hi>Conarus,</hi> ſucceeded to his father <hi>Mogallus,</hi> In the yeare of the world 4119. In the yeare of Chriſt 149. A leacherous tyrant. He was impriſoned by his Nobles, and died in priſon in the 14. yeare of his reigne: and <hi>Argadus,</hi> a Noble man, was made Governour.</p>
            <p n="25">XXV. <hi>Ethodius</hi> 1. <hi>Mogallus</hi> ſiſters ſonne, began to reigne in the yeare of the worlde 4133. In the yeare of Chriſt 163. He was a good prince. He was ſlaine by an Harper, in the 33. yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="26">XXVI. <hi>Satraell,</hi> ſucceeded to his brother <hi>Ethodius</hi> 1. In the yeare of the world 4165. In the yeare of Chriſt 195. A cruell tyrant. He was ſlaine by his owne Courteours, in the 4. yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="27">XXVII. <hi>Donald</hi> 1. the firſt Chriſtian King of Scotland, ſucceeded to his brother <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traell</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:17415:6"/>in the yeare of the world 4169. In the yeare of Chriſt 199. A good and religious King. He was the firſt of the Kings of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land that coyned money of golde and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Hee died in the eighteenth yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="28">XXVIII. <hi>Ethodius</hi> 2. <hi>Ethodius</hi> 1. ſonne, began to reigne in the yeare of the worlde 4186. In the yeare of Chriſt 216. An vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe and baſe mynded King, gouerned by his Nobles. Hee was ſlayne by his owne Guarde, in the 16. yeare of his Reigne.</p>
            <p n="29">XXIX. <hi>Athirco,</hi> ſucceeded to his father <hi>Ethodius</hi> 2. in the yeare of the world 4201. In the yeare of Chriſt 231. A valiant prince in the beginning, but hee degenerated and became vitious, and beeing hardly perſued by his Nobles for his wicked life, ſlewe himſelfe in the 12 yeare. of his Reigne.</p>
            <p n="30">XXX. <hi>Nathalocus,</hi> brother ſonne (as ſome write) to <hi>Athirco,</hi> began to reign in the year of the world 4212. In the yeare of Chriſt 242. A cruell tyrant, ſlaine by his Nobles, and caſt away into a privie, in the 11. yeare of his Reigne.</p>
            <p n="31">XXXI. <hi>Findocus, Athirco</hi> his ſonne, began to reigne in the yeare of the world 4223. In the yeare of Chriſt 253. A good King
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17415:6"/>and valiant, Slaine by feigned Hunters, at the inſtigation of <hi>Donald,</hi> Lord of the <hi>Iles</hi> his brother, in the 11. yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="32">XXXII. <hi>Donald</hi> 2. ſucceeded to his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Findocus,</hi> in the yeare of the worlde 4234. In the yeare of Chriſt 264. A good prince. Hee was wounded in battell, and being overcome, died of diſpleaſure in the firſt yeare of his Reigne.</p>
            <p n="33">XXXIII. <hi>Donald</hi> 3. Lord of <hi>Iles,</hi> brother to <hi>Findocus,</hi> began to reigne in the yeare of worlde 4235. In the yeare of Chriſt 265. A cruell tyrant, ſlaine by <hi>Crathilinthus,</hi> his ſucceſſour, in the 12. yeare of his Reigne.</p>
            <p n="34">XXXIIII. <hi>Crathilinthus, Findocus</hi> ſonne, began to reigne in the yeare of the worlde 4247. In the yeare of Chriſt 277. A va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant and a godly King, he purged the land from the Idolatrous ſuperſtition of the <hi>Dru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ydes,</hi> and planted the ſincere Chriſtian reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. Hee died in peace in the 24. yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="35">XXXV. <hi>Fincormachus,</hi> father brother ſonne to <hi>Crathilinthus,</hi> began his reigne in the yeare of the world 4271. In the yeare of Chriſt 301. A godly King and valiant. Hee was a worthy promover of the Kingdome of Chriſt in Scotland. Hee died in peace in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17415:7"/>the 47. yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="36">
               <hi>XXXVI. Romachus</hi> brothers ſonne to <hi>Crathilinthus</hi> began to reigne in the yeare of the worlde 4318. In the yeare of Chriſt 348. A cruell tyrant, ſlayne by his Nobles, and his head ſtriken off, in the third yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="37">
               <hi>XXXVII. Anguſianus, Crathilinthus</hi> bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſonne, ſucceeded to <hi>Romachus</hi> in the yeare of the worlde 4321. In the yeare of Chriſt 351. A good King, ſlayne in battell by the <hi>Pictes,</hi> in the 3. yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="38">
               <hi>XXXVIII. Fethelmachus,</hi> another bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſonne, of <hi>Crathilinthus,</hi> hee began to reigne in the yeare of the world 4324. In the yeare of Chriſt 354. Hee was a valiant King, for he overcame the <hi>Pictes,</hi> and ſlew their King. Hee was betrayed to the <hi>Pictes</hi> by an Harper, and ſlayne by them in his owne Chamber in the 3. Yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="39">
               <hi>XXXIX. Eugenius</hi> 1. <hi>Fincormachus</hi> ſon, began to reigne in the yeare of the world 4327. In the yeare of Chriſt 357. A va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant, juſt, and good King. Hee was ſlayne in battell by the <hi>Pictes</hi> and <hi>Romaines</hi> in the 3. yeare of his reigne. And the whole <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Nation was vtterly expelled the <hi>Ile</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:17415:7"/>by the <hi>Pictes</hi> and <hi>Romaines,</hi> and remained in exile, about the ſpace of 44. yeares.</p>
            <p n="40">
               <hi>XL. Fergus</hi> 2. <hi>Erthus</hi> ſonnes, ſonne to <hi>Ethodius, Eugenius</hi> the firſt his brother, retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning into <hi>Scotland,</hi> with the helpe of the <hi>Danes</hi> and <hi>Gotthes,</hi> and his owne Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who were gathered to him out of all the countreys where they were diſperſed, conquered his kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> againe out of the <hi>Romaines</hi> and <hi>Pictes</hi> hands. Hee began his reigne, In the the yeare of the world 4374. In the yeare of Chriſt 404. He was a wiſe, valiant and good King. He was ſlayne by the <hi>Romaines</hi> in the 16. yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="41">
               <hi>XLI. Eugenius</hi> 2. <hi>Fergus</hi> 2. ſon ſucceeded to his father, In the yeare of the worlde 4390. In the yeare of Chriſt 420. He was a valiant and a good prince. Hee ſubdued the <hi>Britones,</hi> and died in the thirtie-two yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="42">
               <hi>XLII. Dongardus</hi> ſucceeded to his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Eugenius</hi> 2. In the yeare of the worlde 4421. In the yeare of Chriſt 451. A godly, wiſe and valiant prince. He died in the 5. yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="43">
               <hi>XLIII. Constantine</hi> 1. ſucceeded to his brother <hi>Dongardus,</hi> In the yeare of the world
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17415:8"/>4427. In the yeare of Chriſt 457. A wicked prince. Hee was ſlayne by a Noble man in the <hi>Iles,</hi> whoſe daughter he had deſiled, in the 22. yeare of his Reigne.</p>
            <p n="44">
               <hi>XLIIII. Congallus</hi> 1. <hi>Dongardus</hi> ſonne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to reigne in the yeare of the worlde 4449: In the yeare of Chriſt 479. Hee was a good and quyer Prince: and died in great peace, in the twentie and two yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="45">XLV. <hi>Goranus,</hi> or <hi>Conranus,</hi> ſucceeded to his Brother <hi>Congallus</hi> the firſt, in the yeare of the worlde 4471: and in the yeare of Chriſt 501. A good and wyſe Prince. Hee died even in the thirtie and fourth yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="46">
               <hi>XLVI. Eugenius</hi> the thirde, the ſonne of <hi>Congallus,</hi> ſucceeded to his Father, in the yeare of the worlde 4505: and in the yeare of Chriſt 535. Hee was a wyſe King, and a good Iuſtitiar: and died in the twentie and third yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="47">
               <hi>XLVII. Congallus</hi> the ſecond, or <hi>Conval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> ſucceeded to his Brother <hi>Eugenius</hi> the third, in the yeare of the worlde 4528: and in the yeare of Chriſt 558. A verie good Prince: and died in peace in the eleventh yeare of his Reigne.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:17415:8"/>
            <p n="48">XLVIII. <hi>Kinnatillus</hi> ſucceeded to his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Congallus</hi> the ſecond, in the yeare of the worlde 4539: and in the yeare of Chriſt 569. Hee was a good Prince: and died (alace) in the firſt yeare of his Reigne.</p>
            <p n="49">
               <hi>XLIX. Aidanus,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Conranus,</hi> began his Reigne in the Yeare of the world 4540: and in the Yeare of Chriſt 570. A verie godlie and good Prince: who reigned thirtie and fiue Yeares, and deceaſſed in great peace.</p>
            <p n="50">L. <hi>Kennethus</hi> the firſt, ſur-named <hi>Keir,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Congallus</hi> the ſeconde, beganne to reigne in the Yeare of the worlde 4575: and in the Yeare of Chriſt 605. A verie peaceable Prince: and departed this life in the firſt Yeare of his Reigne.</p>
            <p n="51">LI. <hi>Eugenius</hi> the fourth, the ſonne of <hi>Aidanus,</hi> began his Reigne in the Yeare of the world 4576: and in the Yeare of our Saviour 606. A valiant and good King: and died in the ſixteenth Yeare of his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie Reigne.</p>
            <p n="52">LII. <hi>Ferquhard</hi> the firſt ſucceeded to his Father <hi>Eugenius</hi> the fourth, in the Yeare of the worlde 4591: and in the Yeare of our Redeemer 621. He was a bloodie Tyrant: and being impriſoned, he ſlew him-ſelfe in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17415:9"/>the twelft yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="53">LIII. <hi>Donald</hi> the fourth, ſucceeded to his brother <hi>Ferqubard</hi> the firſt, in the Yeare of the worlde 4602: and in the Yeare of Chriſt 632. Hee was a good and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious King: he was drowned in the Water of <hi>Tay,</hi> while he was a-fiſhing, in the foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Yeare of his Reigne.</p>
            <p n="54">LIIII. <hi>Ferquhard</hi> the ſecond, ſucceeded to his Brother <hi>Donald</hi> the fourth, in the Yeare of the Worlde 4616: And in the Yeare of Chriſt 646. A verie Wicked man. Hee was bitten by a Wolfe in hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: of the which enſued a Fever, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he died in the eighteenth Yeare of his Reigne.</p>
            <p n="55">LV. <hi>Maldvine, Donald</hi> the fourth his Sonne, beganne to Reigne in the Yeare of the Worlde 4634: and in the Yeare of Chriſt 664. A good Prince, ſtrangled by his Wife, who ſuſpected him of Adulterie, in the twentie Yeare of his Reigne.</p>
            <p n="56">LVI. <hi>Eugemus</hi> the fift, <hi>Maldvine</hi> his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſonne, began to Reigne in the yeare of the Worlde 4654: and in the yeare of Chriſt 684. A falſe Prince, ſlaine by the <hi>Pictes</hi> in Battaile in the fourth yeare of his Reigne.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:17415:9"/>
            <p n="57">LVII. <hi>Eugenius</hi> the ſixt, <hi>Ferquhard</hi> the ſecond his ſonne, beganne to Reigne in the Yeare of the worlde 4658: and in the Yeare of Chriſt 688. A good Prince: he died in Peace in the tenth Yeare of his Reigne.</p>
            <p n="58">LVIII. <hi>Ambirkelethus, Findanus</hi> ſonne, <hi>Eugenius</hi> the fift ſonne, beganne to reigne in the Yeare of the worlde 4667: and in the Yeare of Chriſt 697. Hee was ſlaine by the ſhotte of an Arrow: by whom it was ſhotte, it is vnknowne, (a vicious Prince) in the Seconde yeare of his Reigne.</p>
            <p n="59">
               <hi>LIX. Eugenius</hi> the ſeuenth, ſucceeded to his brother <hi>Ambirkelethus,</hi> in the yeare of the Worlde 4669: and in the yeare of Chriſt 699. Hee died in peace in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteenth yeare of his Reigne. A good Prince.</p>
            <p n="60">
               <hi>LX. Mordacus, Ambirkelethus</hi> ſonne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to reigne in the yeare of the worlde 4685: and in the yeare of Chriſt 715. A good Prince. Hee died in the ſixteenth yeare of his Reigne.</p>
            <p n="61">
               <hi>LXI. Etſinus, Eugenius</hi> the ſeaventh his ſonne, beganne to reigne in the yeare of the Worlde 4700: And in the yeare of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17415:10"/>Chriſt 730. He died in Peace in the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth yeare of his Reigne.</p>
            <p n="62">
               <hi>LXII. Eugenius</hi> the eight, <hi>Mordacus</hi> ſonne, beganne to reigne in the yeare of the Worlde 4771: And in the yeare of Chriſt 761. A good Prince in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his reigne: but there-after degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating from his good Life, hee was ſlaine by his Nobles, in the third yeare of his Reigne.</p>
            <p n="63">
               <hi>LXIII. Fergus</hi> the third, <hi>Etſinus</hi> ſonne, beganne to reigne in the yeare of the world 4734: and in the Yeare of Chriſt 764. A leacherous Prince, poyſoned by his Wiſe in the third yeare of his Reigne.</p>
            <p n="64">
               <hi>LXIIII. Solvathius Engenius</hi> the eight ſonne, beganne to reigne in the yeare of the Worlde 4737: and in the Yeare of Chriſt 767. A good Prince, hee died in peace in the twentie Yeare of his Reigne.</p>
            <p n="65">
               <hi>LXV. Achaius, Etſinus</hi> ſonne, beganne to reigne in the yeare of the worlde foure thouſand 757: and in the yeare of Chriſt 787. A peaceable, good and godlie prince. Hee made a league with <hi>Charles le Maigne,</hi> Emperour, and King of <hi>France,</hi> which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth inviolablie keeped to this daye. He died in the thirtie and two yeare of his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17415:10"/>reigne.</p>
            <p n="66">
               <hi>LXVI. Congallus,</hi> or <hi>Convallus, Achaius</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers brothers ſonne, beganne to reigne in the yeare of the worlde 4789: and in the yeare of Chriſt 819. A good prince, hee died in the fift yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="67">
               <hi>LXVII. Dongallus, Solvathius</hi> ſonne, ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded in the yeare of the Worlde 4794: and in the yeare of Chriſt 824. A valiant and good Prince. Hee was drowned com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming over the river of <hi>Spey,</hi> o warre againſt the <hi>Pictes,</hi> in the ſeaventh yeare of his Reigne.</p>
            <p n="68">
               <hi>LXVIII. Alpinus Achaius</hi> ſonne, began to reigne in the Yeare of the worlde 4801: and in the Yeare of Chriſt 831. A good Prince. Hee was taken in Battell, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed by the <hi>Pictes,</hi> in the third yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="69">LXIX. <hi>Kenneth</hi> the ſecond, ſurnamed the Great, ſucceeded to his father <hi>Alpinus,</hi> In the yeare of the Worlde 4804: and in the yeare of Chriſt 834. A good and a Valiant Prince. Hee vtterlie euerthrew the <hi>Pictes</hi> in diuers Battelles, expelled them out of the Land, and joyned the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the <hi>Pictes</hi> to the Crowne of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Hee died in peace in twentie yeare of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17415:11"/>his reigne.</p>
            <p n="70">LXX. <hi>Donald</hi> the fift, ſucceeded to his brother <hi>Kenneth</hi> the ſecond, in the yeare of the worlde 4824: and in the yeare of Chriſt 854. A wicked Prince: hee ſlewe himſelfe in the fift yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="71">LXXI. <hi>Constantine</hi> the ſecond, <hi>Kenneth</hi> the ſecond his ſonne, beganne to reigne in the yeare of the worlde 4829: and in the yeare of Chriſt 859. A valiant Prince. Hee was ſlaine by the <hi>Danes</hi> in a cruell bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell ſtricken at <hi>Carraill</hi> in <hi>Fife,</hi> in the ſixe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="72">LXXII. <hi>Ethus,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Alipes, Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> the ſecond his ſonne, ſucceeded to his Father, in the yeare of the Worlde 4844: and in the yeare of Chriſt 874. A vitious Prince: hee was impriſoned by his Nobles, where he died in the ſecond yeare of his Reigne.</p>
            <p n="73">LXXIII. <hi>Gregorie,</hi> ſurnamed the Great, <hi>Dongallus</hi> ſonne the ſeconde, beganne to reigne in the yeare of the worlde 4846: and in the yeare of Chriſt 876. A valiant, victorious and renowned prince through the worlde in his time: hee died in peace in the eighteenth yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="74">LXXIIII. <hi>Donald</hi> the ſixt, <hi>Constantine</hi> the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17415:11"/>ſecond his ſonne, beganne to reigne in the yeare of the Worlde 4863: and in the yeare of Chriſt 893. A valiant Prince. Hee died in peace, beeing beloued of his Subjectes, in the eleuenth Yeare of his Reigne.</p>
            <p n="75">LXXV. <hi>Constanthie</hi> the third, <hi>Ethus Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes</hi> ſonne, beganne to reigne in the yeare of the worlde 4874: and in the yeare of Chriſt 904. Hee was a valiant King, yet hee proſpered not in his Warres againſt <hi>England:</hi> and therefore, beeing wearie of his Life, hee became a Monke, and died after he had, reigned fourtie yeares as King.</p>
            <p n="76">LXXVI. <hi>Malcolme</hi> the firſt, <hi>Donald</hi> the ſixt his ſonne, beganne to reigne in the yeare of the worlde 4913: and in the yeare of Chriſt 943. A valiant prince, and a good Iuſtitiar: He was ſlaine in <hi>Murray</hi> by a conſpiracie of his owne Subjectes, in the ninth yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="77">LXXVII. <hi>Indulfus, Constantine</hi> the third his ſonne, beganne to reigne in the yeare of the worlde 4922: and in the yeare of Chriſt 952. A valiant, and a good prince. Hee had manie battailes with the <hi>Danes,</hi> whome hee overcame: but in the ende
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17415:12"/>hee was ſlaine by them in a ſtratageme of Warre, in the ninth yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="78">LXXVIII. <hi>Duffus, Malcolme</hi> the firſt his ſonne, beganne to reigne in the yeare of the Worlde 4931: and in the yeare of Chriſt 961. A good Prince, and a ſeuere Iuſtitiar. Hee was ſlaine by one <hi>Donald,</hi> at <hi>Forres</hi> in <hi>Murray,</hi> and was buried ſecretlie vnder the Brig of a River beſide <hi>Kinloſſe:</hi> but the matter was reuealed, and the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer and his wife, that conſented there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to were ſeuerelie puniſhed. Hee reigned fiue yeares.</p>
            <p n="79">LXXIX. <hi>Culenus, Indulfus</hi> ſonne, beganne to reigne in the yeare of the worlde 4936: and in the yeare of Chriſt 966. An vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and an effeminate prince. Hee was ſlaine at <hi>Methwen;</hi> by <hi>Radardus,</hi> a Noble man, whoſe Daughter hee had defiled, in the fourth yeare of his Reigne.</p>
            <p n="80">LXXX. <hi>Kenneth</hi> the third, <hi>Duffus</hi> Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, beganne to reigne in the yeare of the Worlde 4940: and in the yeare of Chriſt 970. A valiant, and a Wiſe prince: But in the ende hee became Cruell, and ſlew <hi>Malcolme</hi> his Brothers Sonne: and in GODS Iudgement, who ſuffereth not Innocent blood to bee vnpuniſhed, hee
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17415:12"/>was ſlaine by a ſtrange engine, an Image fixed in a Wall, at <hi>Fetticarne,</hi> by the meanes of a Noble woman there, called <hi>Fenella,</hi> in the twentie foure yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="81">LXXXI. <hi>Constantine</hi> the fourth, ſurna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Calvus, Culenus</hi> Sonne, beganne to reigne in the yeare of the worlde 4964: and in the yeare of Chriſt 994. An uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Crowne. Hee was ſlaine in Battell at the Towne of <hi>Crawmond,</hi> in <hi>Lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian,</hi> in the ſecond yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="82">LXXXII. <hi>Grimus, Duffus</hi> Sonne, beganne to reigne in the yeare of the worlde 4966: and in the yeare of Chriſt 996. A vicious prince: he was ſlaine in Battell by <hi>Malcolme</hi> the ſecond, his ſucceſſor, in the eight yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="83">LXXXIII. <hi>Malcolme</hi> the ſecond, <hi>Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth</hi> the third his Sonne, beganne to reigne in the yeare of the Worlde 4974: And in the yeare of Chriſt 1004. A Valiant and a wiſe prince: who made manie good Lawes, of the which a few are yet extant. Hee was Slayne by a Conſpiracie of his Nobles, at the Caſtell of <hi>Glammes:</hi> who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſlaughter, thinking to eſcape, were drowned in the Loch of <hi>Forfar,</hi> for it
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17415:13"/>being Winter, and the Loch frozen, and couered with Snow, the Yee brake, and they fell in, ſhewing euen the Righteous Iudgement of GOD. He reigned thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yeares.</p>
            <p n="84">LXXXIIII. <hi>Duncane</hi> the firſt, <hi>Beatrix, Malcolme</hi> the Second his Daughters Sonne, began to reigne in the yeare of the worlde 5004: and in the yeare of Chriſt 1034. A good and a modeſt Prince. Hee was ſlaine by <hi>Mackbeth</hi> traiterouſlie, in the ſixt yeare of his Reigne.</p>
            <p n="85">LXXXV. <hi>Mackbeth, Dovada Malcolme</hi> the ſecond his daughters ſonne, beganne to Reigne in the yeare of the worlde 5010: and in the yeare of Chriſt 1040. In the beginning of his reigne hee behaued him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe as a good and juſt Prince: but there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after hee degenerated into a Cruell Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. Hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſlaine by his Succeſſour <hi>Malcolme</hi> the third, in battell, in the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteenth yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="86">LXXXVI. <hi>Malcolme</hi> the third, ſurna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Cammoir, Duncane</hi> the firſt his ſonne, beganne to reigne in the yeare of the world 5027: and in the yeare of Chriſt 1057. A verie Religious and valiant Prince: He married <hi>Margaret,</hi> daughter to <hi>Edward,</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17415:13"/>the OVT-LAW, ſonne vnto <hi>Edward,</hi> ſur-named YRON-SIDE, King of ENG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND; a verie good and religious Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, according vnto thoſe times: vvho bare vnto him ſixe Sonnes, &amp; two Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. The Sonnes were, <hi>Edward</hi> the Prince, <hi>Edmond, Etheldred, Edgar, Alexander,</hi> and <hi>David.</hi> The Daughters were, <hi>Mathildis,</hi> or <hi>Maude,</hi> ſur-named BONA, Wife vnto <hi>Henrie</hi> the firſt, ſur-named BEAVCLERKE, King of ENGLAND: of whoſe Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues is yet extant amongſt vs this olde EPIGRAMME:</p>
            <q>
               <l>Prospera non laetam fecere, nee aspera triſtem,</l>
               <l>Prospera terror ei, aspera riſus crant,</l>
               <l>Non decor effecit fragilem, non ſceptra ſuperbam,</l>
               <l>Sola potens humilis, ſola pudica decens.</l>
            </q>
            <p>That is to ſay in Engliſh:</p>
            <q>
               <l>Proſperitie rejoyced her not:</l>
               <l>To her Griefe was no paine.</l>
               <l>Proſperitie affrayde her eke:</l>
               <l>Affliction was her gaine.</l>
               <l>Her Beautie was no cauſe of fall:</l>
               <l>In Royall State not proude.</l>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:17415:14"/>
               <l>Humble alone in Dignitie:</l>
               <l>In Beautie onelie good.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Shee founded the Kirke of <hi>Carleill.</hi> Now the other daughter was <hi>Marie,</hi> vvife unto <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtathius,</hi> Earle of <hi>Boloigne.</hi> King <hi>Malcolme</hi> builded the Kirkes of <hi>Durehame,</hi> and <hi>Dum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fermeling.</hi> Hee, with his ſonne Prince <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> were both ſlaine, at the ſiedge of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke,</hi> in the thirtie and ſixt yeare of his reigne, by <hi>Robert Mowbray,</hi> ſur-named <hi>Pierce-eye.</hi> Hee was firſt buried at <hi>Tinmouth:</hi> but afterwardes his corpſe was removed to <hi>Dumfermeling,</hi> and buried there.</p>
            <p n="87">LXXXVII. <hi>Donald</hi> the leanenth, ſur-na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Bane,</hi> uſurped the Crowne, after the death of his brother: in the yeare of the Worlde 5063: and in the yeare of Chriſt 1093. But hee was expelled in the verie firſt yeare that he began to reigne, by <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane</hi> the ſeconde, King <hi>Malcolmes</hi> thirde ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtarde ſonne.</p>
            <p n="88">LXXXVIII. The ſaid <hi>Duncane</hi> the ſecond uſurped the Crowne, in the yeare of the vvorlde 5064: and in the yeare of Chriſt 1094. A raſh and fooliſh Prince: and by the procurement of <hi>Donald</hi> the ſeaventh he was ſlaine in the <hi>Thane</hi> of the <hi>Meirnes,</hi> by
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17415:14"/>
               <hi>Macke-pendir,</hi> vvhen hee had reigned a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more than one yeare.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>Donald</hi> the ſeauenth was made king againe, in the yeare of the vvorlde 5065: and in the yeare of Chriſt 1095. He gaue the <hi>Weſt</hi> and <hi>North</hi> Yles to the king of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi> for to aſſiſt him to attaine unto the Crowne of <hi>Scotland.</hi> But within three yeares hee was taken captiue, by <hi>Edgar:</hi> his Eyes were both put out: and after much miſerie, hee died moſte odiouſlie, even lying in Priſon.</p>
            <p n="89">LXXXIX. <hi>Edgar, Malcolme</hi> the thirde his ſonne, beganne his reigne in the yeare of the Worlde 5068: and in the yeare of our Saviour 1098. Hee builded the Priorie of <hi>Coldinghame.</hi> Hee reigned nine yeares, and was a good and loving Prince. But hee died without ſucceſſion, at <hi>Dundie,</hi> and was buried at <hi>Dumfermeling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="90">XC. <hi>Alexander</hi> the firſt, ſur-named The <hi>Fearce,</hi> ſucceeded unto his brother, in the yeare of the World 5077: and in the yeare of Chriſt 1107. A verie good and valiant Prince indeede. Hee builded the Abbacies of <hi>Scone,</hi> and of Sainct <hi>Colmes-Inch.</hi> And hee tooke to vvyfe <hi>Sibylla,</hi> Daughter un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>William,</hi> the good Duke of <hi>Normandie,</hi> &amp;c. <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:17415:15"/>at <hi>Striviling:</hi> from whence his dead corpſe was ſolemnlie tranſported vnto <hi>Aber-bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thocke,</hi> and buried there.</p>
            <p n="94">XCIIII. <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſecond, ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to his Father <hi>William,</hi> In the yeare of the worlde 5184: and in the yeare of Chriſt 1214. A good Prince: Hee mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried <hi>Ieane,</hi> daughter to <hi>Iohn</hi> King of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> by whome hee had no Succeſſion. After her death, he married <hi>Marie,</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to <hi>Ingelrame,</hi> Earle of <hi>Coucey</hi> in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> by whome hee had <hi>Alexander</hi> the thirde. Hee died at <hi>Kernerie,</hi> in the Weſt <hi>Iles,</hi> and was buried at <hi>Mel-roſſe,</hi> in the thirtie and fiue yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p n="95">XCV. <hi>Alexander</hi> the third, ſucceeded to his father, in the yeare of the worlde 5219: and in the yeare of Chriſt 1249. A good Prince. He married firſt <hi>Margaret,</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to <hi>Henry</hi> the third, King of <hi>England:</hi> by whome hee had <hi>Alexander</hi> the Prince: who married the Earle of <hi>Flanders</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: <hi>Dauid,</hi> and <hi>Margaret,</hi> who married <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonanus,</hi> or as ſome call him, <hi>Ericus,</hi> ſonne to <hi>Magnus</hi> the fourth, King of <hi>Norway:</hi> who bare to him a daughter, commonly called the <hi>Mayden</hi> of <hi>Norway:</hi> in whome King <hi>William</hi> his whole poſteritie failed,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17415:15"/>and the Crowne of <hi>Scotland</hi> returned to the poſteritie of <hi>Dauid,</hi> Earle of <hi>Hunting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doun,</hi> King <hi>Malcolme</hi> the fourth, and King <hi>William</hi> his brother. After his ſonnes death, (for they died before himſelfe, without Succeſſion) in hope of Poſteritie, hee married <hi>Ioleta,</hi> Daughter to the Earle of <hi>Dreux</hi> in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> by whome hee had no Succeſſion. Hee builded the croſſe Kirke of <hi>Peibles.</hi> He died of a fall off his Horſe vpon the Sandes betwixt Eaſter and We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>King-borne,</hi> in the thirtie and ſeaven yeare of his reigne: And was buried at <hi>Dumfermeling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the death of <hi>Alexander</hi> the third, which was in the yeare of the Worlde 5255, and in the yeare of Chriſt 1285, there were Sixe Regentes appointed to rule <hi>Scotland.</hi> For the South-ſide of <hi>Forthe,</hi> were appointed <hi>Robert,</hi> the Arche-Biſhop of <hi>Glaſgowe, Iohn Cummin,</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> the great Steward of <hi>Scotland.</hi> For the North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of <hi>Forthe, Mak-duffe,</hi> Earle of <hi>Fife; Iohn Cummin,</hi> Earle of <hi>Buchan;</hi> and <hi>William Fraſer,</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Sainct-Andrewes:</hi> who ruled the Land about the ſpace of ſeauen yeares, untill the Controuerſie was decided be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17415:16"/>
               <hi>Iohn Ballioll,</hi> and <hi>Robert Bruyſe,</hi> Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father to <hi>Robert Bruyſe,</hi> the King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> come of the two eldeſt daughters of <hi>David</hi> Earle of <hi>Huntingdoun:</hi> for <hi>Henrie Hastings,</hi> who married the youngeſt daughter, put not in his ſute with the reſt: and therefore there is little ſpoken of him.</p>
            <p n="95">XCV. <hi>Iohn Ballioll</hi> was preferred to <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Bruyſe,</hi> to bee King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> by <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the firſt, ſur-named <hi>Lang-ſhankes,</hi> King of ENGLAND, who was choſen to bee Iudge of the controverſie, vpon a Condition, That hee ſhould acknowledge him as Superiour: which condition (like an vnworthie man) hee received. He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne his reigne in the yeare of the world 5263: and in the yeare of Chriſt 1293. Hee was a vaine-glorious man, little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting the Weale of his Countrey. Hee had not reigned fullie foure Yeares, when hee was expelled by the ſaide <hi>Edward:</hi> and leaving <hi>Scotland,</hi> departed into the partes of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> where hee died long there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after in exile. And ſo <hi>Scotland</hi> was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a King, and Governement, the ſpace of nine yeares: during which ſpace, the ſaide <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, <hi>Lang-ſhankes,</hi> cruellie op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17415:16"/>the Land, deſtroyed the whole auncient Monuments of the Kingdome, and ſhed much innocent blood.</p>
            <p n="96">XCVI. <hi>Robert Bruyſe,</hi> began to reigne in the yeare of the worlde 5276: and in the yeare of Chriſt 1306. A valiant, good and wiſe King. In the beginning of his reigne, hee was ſubject to great miſerie and affliction, beeing oppreſſed by <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> but at length, hauing ouer-come and vanquiſhed <hi>Edward</hi> the ſeconde, of <hi>Carnar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>van,</hi> at the Fielde of <hi>Bannocke-burne,</hi> by the helpe of GOD, hee deliuered his owne Countrey of <hi>Scotland</hi> from the ſlauerie of <hi>England:</hi> yea, and ſet it at full libertie, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling euen by force of Armes, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation quite out of the Land.</p>
            <p>Hee married firſt <hi>Iſabell,</hi> daughter vnto the Earle of <hi>Marre:</hi> who bare vnto him a comelie daughter, called <hi>Marjorie,</hi> wife vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Walter,</hi> the Great <hi>Steward</hi> of <hi>Scotland:</hi> of whoſe happie Race is ruling this day not onelie in <hi>Scotland,</hi> but alſo over whole <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane, Ireland,</hi> &amp;c. as yee ſhall heare, GOD willing, anone, in the owne place.</p>
            <p>Nowe after the death of King <hi>Robert the Bruyce</hi> his firſt wife, <hi>Iſabell,</hi> the Earle of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17415:17"/>
               <hi>Marre</hi> his Daughter, as ſayde is, hee mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried another of the ſame name, <hi>Iſabell,</hi> who vvas the onelie Daughter, and Heretrixe, unto <hi>Haymerus de Burc,</hi> Earle of <hi>Hultonia,</hi> or <hi>Hulſter,</hi> in <hi>Ireland:</hi> and ſhee bare unto him one goodlie Sonne, and two Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, to wit, <hi>David</hi> the ſeconde, <hi>Margaret,</hi> the Counteſſe of <hi>Sootherland,</hi> and her youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt Daughter <hi>Maude,</hi> vvho died in her childhood. This good King, after he had reigned twentie and foure yeares, hee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his toylſome dayes at <hi>Cardroſſe,</hi> and was honourablie buried at <hi>Dumfermeling,</hi> with great ſolemnitie.</p>
            <p n="98">XCVIII. <hi>David,</hi> the ſecond <hi>Bruyce,</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded unto his father, in the yeare of the Worlde fiue thouſand, &amp; three hundreth: and in the yeare of our Redemption, one thouſand, three hundreth, and thirtie. Hee was a good prince, and ſubject unto verie much affliction in his youth: for firſt after the death of <hi>Thomas Ranulph</hi> his Regent, hee was forced to flee into <hi>France,</hi> euen for ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guarde of his lyfe. And after certaine years returning homewardes to <hi>Scotland,</hi> was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken priſoner at the Battell of <hi>Durhame,</hi> by the <hi>Engliſh-men,</hi> and holden almoſt twelue
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17415:17"/>yeares captiue in <hi>England.</hi> But at length, as GOD vvould, hee was reſtored to his free libertie: and hee married firſt <hi>Ieane,</hi> Daughter unto <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, King of faire <hi>England:</hi> and after her death hee mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried <hi>Margaret Logie,</hi> Daughter unto Sir <hi>Iohn Logie,</hi> Knight. And yet hee died with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out anie ſucceſſion, in the fourtieth yeare of his reigne, at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and vvas bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried at <hi>Holie-Roode-houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="99">XCIX. <hi>Edward Ballioll,</hi> ſonne to <hi>Iohn Ballioll,</hi> vſurped the Crowne of <hi>Scotland,</hi> beeing aſſiſted by <hi>Edward</hi> the third, King of ENGLAND, in the Yeare of the Worlde 5302: and in the Yeare of Chriſt 1332. But hee was expelled at length by <hi>Dauid</hi> the ſeconde his Regents, and <hi>Dauid</hi> the ſeconde eſtabliſhed King.</p>
            <p n="100">C. <hi>Robert</hi> the ſecond, ſurnamed <hi>Blear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eye,</hi> the firſt of the <hi>Stewardes,</hi> ſonne to <hi>Walter Steward,</hi> and <hi>Marjorie Bruyſe,</hi> King <hi>Robert Bruyſe</hi> his Daughter, ſucceeded to his Mothers Brother, In the yeare of the Worlde 5341: and in the yeare of Chriſt 1371. A good and a Peaceable Prince. He married firſt <hi>Eufeme,</hi> Daughter to <hi>Hugh,</hi> Earle of <hi>Roſſe:</hi> who bare vnto him <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:17415:18"/>Earle of <hi>Stratherne; Walter;</hi> Earle of <hi>Athol,</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> Earle of <hi>Buchan,</hi> Lord <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neynoch.</hi> And after her deceaſſe, (euen for the affection which hee bare unto his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren which hee had begotten before hee was firſt married) hee married <hi>Elizabeth Mure,</hi> Daughter unto Sir <hi>Adam Mure,</hi> a worthie Knight: who (afore-times) had borne unto him <hi>Iohn,</hi> who there-after was called <hi>Robert</hi> the thirde, Earle of <hi>Carricke: Robert,</hi> Earle of <hi>Fyffe</hi> and <hi>Menteith:</hi> and <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feme,</hi> wife to <hi>Iames,</hi> Earle of <hi>Dowglas.</hi> But at length this good Prince behoved to goe the way of all fleſh: and when hee had reigned happilie about nineteene yeares, he departed this lyfe in peace, at <hi>Dun-Donalde,</hi> and was ſolemnlie buried at <hi>Scone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="101">CI. <hi>Robert</hi> the thirde, ſur-named <hi>Iohn Farne-yeare,</hi> ſucceeded unto his father, in the yeare of the Worlde, fiue thouſande, three hundreth, and three-ſcore: and in the yeare of our bleſſed Saviour, Chriſt Ieſus, one thouſand, three hundreth, foure-ſcore, and ten. Hee was a quiet and peaceable Prince: and tooke to wyfe <hi>Annabell Drum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> daughter unto the Laird of <hi>Stob-hall:</hi> who bare unto him <hi>David</hi> the Prince, Duke
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:17415:18"/>of <hi>Rotheſay,</hi> that died in priſon of verie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame famine, at <hi>Falkland:</hi> and <hi>Iames</hi> the firſt, taken captiue in his voyage to <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and deteined a captiue, againſt all equitie, almoſt the ſpace of eighteene Yeares in <hi>England.</hi> Hee died of diſpleaſure at <hi>Rothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay,</hi> when hee heard of the death of his one ſonne, and captiuitie of the other. Hee was buried at <hi>Paiſley,</hi> in the ſixteenth yeare of his reigne.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>Robert,</hi> Earle of <hi>Fyffe</hi> and <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teith,</hi> beganne to gouerne the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in the yeare of the Worlde, fiue thouſand, three hundreth, three-ſcore, and ſixteene: and in the yeare of Chriſt, one thouſand, foure hundreth, and ſixe. And hee died in the fourteenth yeare of his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement: <hi>Iames</hi> the firſt being yet holden captiue in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Murdo Steward</hi> ſucceeded to his father, <hi>Robert</hi> Earle of <hi>Fyffe,</hi> in the Gouernement of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in the yeare of the Worlde, fiue thouſand, three hundreth, foure-ſcore, and ten: and in the yeare of our bleſſed Redeemer, one thouſand, foure hundreth, and twentie: and ruled foure yeares: <hi>Iames</hi> the firſt ſtill continuing a captiue in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:17415:19"/>But the father, and his ſonne <hi>Walter,</hi> there-after, were both executed, euen by the ſayde <hi>Iames</hi> the firſt, for oppreſſion of the Subjectes.</p>
            <p n="102">CII. IAMES the firſt, beganne for to reigne in the yeare of the Worlde, 5394: and in the yeare of CHRIST, 1424. Hee was a good, learned, vertuous, and a juſt King. Hee married <hi>Ieane,</hi> Daughter vnto <hi>Iohn,</hi> Duke of <hi>Summer-ſet,</hi> and Marques <hi>Dorcet,</hi> ſonne to <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Ghendt,</hi> the thirde ſonne to the victorious King of <hi>England, Edward</hi> the third: And ſhe bare to him on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie one ſonne, and ſixe daughters; to wit, <hi>Iames</hi> the ſecond; <hi>Margaret,</hi> wyfe to <hi>Lewes,</hi> the eleventh of that name, the Dolphine of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and there-after King: <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the Duches of <hi>Britaine: Ieane,</hi> Counteſſe of <hi>Huntley: Eleonor,</hi> Duches of <hi>Austria: Marie,</hi> wyfe to the Lord of <hi>Campe-Veere:</hi> and <hi>Anna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bella,</hi> who was yet but young.</p>
            <p>This good Prince was ſlaine trayte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſlie, (alace) at <hi>Perth,</hi> by <hi>Walter,</hi> Earle of <hi>Athole,</hi> and <hi>Robert Grahame,</hi> together vvith their pactious Confederates, in the thirtie and one yeare of his Reigne, if wee count from the death of his Father: and in the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:17415:19"/>thirteenth yeare of his Reigne, if wee count from his happie deliverance out of ENGLAND. Hee was buried at the Charter-houſe of <hi>Perth,</hi> the which hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede had builded.</p>
            <p n="103">CIII. IAMES the ſecond, ſucceeded to his Father, in the yeare of the Worlde, 5407: and in the yeare of CHRIST, 1437. A Prince greatlie ſubject to troubles in his youth. Hee married <hi>Marie,</hi> Daughter to <hi>Arnolde,</hi> Duke of <hi>Geldre,</hi> Siſters daughter to <hi>Charles,</hi> ſur-named <hi>Audax,</hi> the laſt Duke of <hi>Burgundie,</hi> &amp;c. And ſhee bare unto him three Sonnes, to wit, <hi>Iames</hi> the third: <hi>Iohn,</hi> Earle of <hi>Marre:</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> Duke of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banie.</hi> More ouer, ſhee bare a daughter un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, called <hi>Marie,</hi> who was firſt married unto <hi>Thomas Boyde,</hi> Earle of <hi>Arrane:</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his decourting, unto <hi>Iames Hammiltoun,</hi> of <hi>Cadſow.</hi> And the King was ſlaine at the ſiedge of <hi>Roxburgh,</hi> in the twentie and fourth yeare of his Reigne.</p>
            <p n="104">CIIII. IAMES the thirde, ſucceeded unto his Father, in the yeare of the World, 5430: and in the yeare of our Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, 1460. A Prince corrupted by wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Courteours, God wots. Hee married
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:17415:20"/>
               <hi>Margaret,</hi> daughter unto <hi>Christianus</hi> the firſt, ſur-named <hi>Dives,</hi> (that is to ſay, <hi>Ritch</hi>) King of <hi>Denmarke, Norway,</hi> and <hi>Sweden.</hi> And when he had reigned twentie &amp; nine yeares, hee was ſlaine at the Fielde and Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell of <hi>Bannocke-Burne,</hi> and Princelie buried at <hi>Cambuſ-Kenneth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="105">CV. IAMES the fourth, ſucceeded to his Father, in the yeare of the Worlde, fiue thouſand, foure hundreth, fiftie, and nine: and in the yeare of IESVS CHRIST, one thouſand, foure hundreth, foure-ſcore, and nine. A verie Noble and Couragious King. Hee married firſt <hi>Margaret,</hi> eldeſt daughter to <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſeaventh, Earle of <hi>Ritchmond,</hi> and there-after King of faire <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> And after her deecaſſe, hee married <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> daughter unto <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, King of <hi>England.</hi> In whoſe two perſones, the two Houſes of <hi>Lancaster</hi> and <hi>Yorke</hi> were united, and the Bloodie Civill Warres of <hi>England</hi> finiſhed. This good Prince was ſlaine at <hi>Flowdon,</hi> by <hi>England,</hi> in the twentie and fift yeare of his Reigne.</p>
            <p n="106">CVI. IAMES the fift, ſucceeded to his father, in the yeare of the Worlde, fiue thouſand, foure hundreth, foure-ſcore, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17415:20"/>foure: and in the yeare of CHRIST, one thouſand, fiue hundreth, and fourteene. A juſt Prince, and ſeuere. Firſt hee mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried <hi>Magdalene,</hi> daughter to <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt, King of <hi>Fraunce:</hi> but ſhe died verie ſhortlie there-after, without anie ſucceſſion. Then hee married <hi>Marie</hi> of <hi>Lorayne,</hi> Duches of <hi>Longe-Ville,</hi> daughter unto <hi>Claude,</hi> Duke of <hi>Guiſe.</hi> Hee died at <hi>Falke-land,</hi> in the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and ninth yeare of his Reigne, and was buried at <hi>Holie-Roode-Houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="107">CVII. MARIE ſucceeded unto her Father, IAMES the fift, in the yeare of the Worlde, fiue thouſand, fiue hundreth, and thirteene: and in the yeare of our bleſſed LORD, one thouſande, fiue hundreth, fourtie, and three. A Princeſſe vertuouſlie inclined. Shee firſt married <hi>Frauncis</hi> the ſeconde, Dolphine of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and there-after King. And after his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſſe, returning home to <hi>Scotland</hi> a Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, ſhee married <hi>Henrie Steward,</hi> Duke of <hi>Albanie,</hi> &amp;c. Lord <hi>Darley,</hi> Sonne to <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi> Earle of <hi>Lennox:</hi> a comelie prince. and Pro-nephew to <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſeuenth, King of ENGLAND: unto whome ſhee bare IAMES the Sixt. But (alace) after eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17415:21"/>yeares captiuitie, ſhee was put to death in ENGLAND: in the yeare of CHRIST 1586: the eight day of Februarie: and lyeth nowe entombed at WEST-MVNSTER.</p>
            <p n="108">CVIII. IAMES the Sixt, ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded unto his Mother, in the yeare of the Worlde, Fiue thouſande, fiue hundreth, thirtie, and ſeauen: and in the yeare of IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVS CHRIST, One thouſand, fiue hundreth, three-ſcore, and ſeauen. A ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie good, Godlie, peaceable, wiſe, and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Prince, as indeede his ſundrie Workes which are alreadie gone foorth in Print, in ſundrie Languages, euen to the view of the whole Worlde; to the great comfort of us, his louing Subjectes, and all others, who truelie profeſſe the Goſpel of Ieſus Chriſt; and to the terror of all Heretiques, Athiſts, and Papiſts, can teſtifie.</p>
            <p>Hee married <hi>Anna,</hi> Daughter to <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dericke</hi> the ſecond, King of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> &amp;c. and to <hi>Sophia, Vlricus</hi> the Duke of <hi>Mechelenburgh</hi> his daughter: vvho bare unto him <hi>Henrie Fredericke</hi> the Prince, who died in the prime of his youth: <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> wyfe to Prince <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:17415:21"/>of the <hi>Rhene,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Charles,</hi> our hopefull Prince, now about the age of 23 yeares.</p>
            <p>The ſayd IAMES the ſixt, euen through GODS prouidence, and righteous Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, is now preſentlie King of Great BRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TANE, FRANCE, &amp; IRELAND: whom wee beſeech euen the GOD of Heauen, upon the knees of our loyall hearts, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue his dayes longer than long amongſt us: yea, that his happie poſteritie remaine ſtill to gouerne ouer ours, to the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der aduancement of GODS Glorie, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of His Elect, euen for euer and euer, <hi>Amen.</hi> 
               <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>From Aberdene, <hi>1623.</hi> Ian. <hi>30.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17415:22"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17415:22"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17415:23"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17415:23"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
